welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us through i'm
joined by my friend
and colleague greg henriques i'm john
varvakey i'm a cognitive psychologist
and a cognitive scientist at the
university of toronto
i do work on and teach on work on the
nature of consciousness
and its relationship to intelligence um
its relationship
to other aspects of cognition and
what i want to do here with greg's
really excellent help in a biological
manner
i want to present an argument greg's
familiar with this argument
i want to present an argument about
trying to
make make an argument that i've been
developing to try and make some progress
on untangling the the the very difficult
problem of
the place of cognition in the world last
time i'll introduce back in a sec
last time greg and i sort of brought up
the two central
problems that we want to wrestle with
around consciousness
um and that um and these are
uh the function the function problem
what does consciousness do
and the nature or generation problem
which is uh
how is it that something like
consciousness exists in has a place in
the otherwise physical naturalistic
world we see ourselves within
greg has forewarned that he and i are
get uh get into
some uh uh interesting uh uh hopefully
fun friction
around physicalism and naturalism i look
forward to that and i think that's a
good segue for
passing it over to greg to introduce
himself right actually physical
naturalism now we're already building
bridges
right that sounds good to me uh yes so
i'm greg henricus i'm a
professor of psychology at james madison
university i
am interested in what i call the problem
of psychology
which gets into what is the science of
behavior and mental process why is that
been such an unbelievable difficult
thing to define with any kind of
consensus
and some of that also takes me into what
i call my unified metapsychology
framework
which offers a new naturalistic
definitional system
uh for mind and matter uh and then i
came to learn about john and all of his
wonderful work uh and have been
dogging him ever since uh so that i can
learn and see
his model of uh consciousness uh
fits uh in a very very exciting way and
fills out an enormous amount of richness
um and that's what i'm looking forward
to teasing out so
i'm really really thrilled to be here
great
thanks greg that's wonderful i realize
i've been mispronouncing your last name
i apologize
uh but uh they covered in the fact that
nobody's pronounces my last name
correctly
all right i'm so useful i don't even
hear that anymore
uh what uh what are we going to try and
do with this well we
are going to try and as i said we're
going to really try and tackle
these uh interconnected problems
of the nature and function of
consciousness but as the subtitle of the
whole series indicates
this is particularly why greg is here
not only for his expertise on psychology
but also because
greg like me is very interested on the
existential and potentially
and we i think i'm going to use this
very broadly greg will often use it in a
more
uh specific sense but i'm going to use
it broadly right now an existential and
therapeutic
ramifications of this coming to
a a deep a different and deeper
understanding
of the nature of consciousness greg and
i are both a little bit uncomfortable
with this word
uh but also but i'll speak it on our
behalf
um we're interested in what you might
call the
spiritual implications of getting right
about or
getting as right as we can i don't want
to be pretentious or humoristic
getting as right as we can about the
nature of consciousness so
i'd like to start and i propose this to
greg and he agreed that this is a good
place to start i'd like to start
with how we got into the problem of
consciousness
um so many of you have seen uh
uh awakening for the meeting crisis
where how do we get into the heart
problem of
the meaning crisis and believe me that
we will keep coming back to that in the
in the course of what we're going to
the two problems are not are not
separable
but i want to do something similar and
get into how did
how did consciousness become such a
difficult thing
for us in particular and
um there's a there's a myriad of places
we could start
and so really in the interests of time
i'm going to start in a place
that i think is sort of optimal for
getting us getting our feet on the
ground for this problem
and that's uh that's descartes response
to the scientific revolution because i
think
the arguments that descartes proposes
there are three arguments
have laid out our cultural cognitive
grammar for thinking about mind
and greg is going to develop this later
right i've laid out the cultural
cognitive grammar of thinking about mine
that we still carry with us today and
and well we need to get we need to get
this answered why is this cultural
cognitive grammar
so attractive
but it is also so problematic and so
damaging to us
like so there's something odd it's like
it's like it's like it's almost like
it's almost like crack it's really
attractive right it's really really
attractive to us it's almost inescapable
to us
and yet we know it and many people much
more
brilliant than myself have pointed out
how this cartesian framework
has been so damaging to us in so many
ways and greg is again gonna
like really develop that i think for us
at length
and so what my main thesis is going to
be
my initial proposal what i'm proposing
to greg
is that the reason why it's so
attractive
is because of the way that conception of
the mind
is so deeply bound up with the
conception of the world
that emerged in the scientific
revolution and because of the success
of the scientific worldview we and
because it is
inseparably bound up with the cartesian
cultural cognitive grammar we are deeply
attracted to this grammar
even though in many ways it is almost
traumatizing to us
both collectively and individually so
great how what do you think about that
brilliant and uh let me rip off that for
just a second so
um you know as a clinician and somebody
studies personality one of the things i
often notice is uh somebody's greatest
strength is also their greatest weakness
right right uh and so i think that there
is something very very enormously
appealing and you'll be able to
articulate that with good
uh you know about this frame it makes
perfect intuitive sense
um i think the connection between the
frame and the modern scientific
revolution is absolutely key
and its disaster is key both
conceptually and to the larger
existential spiritual meaning crisis
that we
reside in and so you know in my own work
i've identified what i call the
enlightenment
gap and the enlightenment gap is that
the modernist
idea of empirical science had two
really difficult problems that they
didn't and no synthetic system was able
to resolve
one of which is this mind matter problem
okay
and the other is what is actually
scientific knowledge relative to
socially constructed knowledge right and
how do we
how do we crisply differentiate those
and we see the emergence of
post-modernism really as
especially in the second one but we see
the problem of psychology in the first
okay all right and so here we can say
here's
descartes one of the fathers although
galileo generally is called the father
of modern science but
um descartes one of the fathers clearly
to giving us the grammar
with with such richness i i through your
work i've come to appreciate how
sophisticated i sort of give descartes a
short shrift in my own
writing historically he's a brilliant
person and gives where i knew he did was
that but his his
work on the mind and consciousness was
really rich
much richer than i was aware of so that
gives us
an opportunity to move into it thank you
greg that was uh
that's a that uh first of all that
bringing out those two problems i just
want to acknowledge that that's good
uh the the uh the sort of the mind body
problem as it's traditionally called
and then the relationship between
scientific knowledge
and socially constructed knowledge i
think that's really that's also
excellent
um and that of course has been the
tortured relationship between
the hard sciences and the humanities or
the hard sciences of the social sciences
and we'll see as we go along that those
problems as you're
intimating are deeply interconnected um
i like what you also mentioned there
about galileo and uh dave carnell talk a
little bit about that in the history
one of the things i find about descartes
that's interesting is
there's a sense in which he is
responding to the spiritual
crisis being caused by the emergence of
the scientific revolution
and and it's no coincidence
that he labeled one of his most
important he titled sorry one of his
most important works
the meditations because he is alluding
to marcus aurelius's meditations
which are a series of spiritual
exercises because he's trying to get
people uh
uh he's trying to give people an
existential response
to the way their world was being torn
asunder by the scientific revolution
and unfortunately that existential
aspect of descartes work is also
uh tended to be uh not properly
remembered and so we're gonna try and
remember it we are going to
respond to that and remember it
throughout what we're doing here
together
did you want to say anything more before
we i propose sort of the first argument
yeah no no that i think we're ready then
to set so that so this
setup is um you know here we are in
the emergence of modernist thinking
science is happening
uh descartes gets his cartesian
coordinates so all of a sudden we start
to mathematically map
behavior and change in particular ways
of course galileo's doing that and now
this whole issue of
the dual world history into a mono world
reality um so yeah no
on the edge of the seat we're excited
this is fun to be doing this together
with you i really appreciate that so
what i'm going to do
is i'm going to take a look at what i
consider descartes three core arguments
um not because i'm trying to convince
you
about the conclusion of these arguments
not at all in fact uh
in a very real sense i'm not convinced
by their
by them right but i want to show you
um i want to bring all us together into
a proper respect for these arguments and
so that we
we can get a deep understanding
of the issue we're facing i talk a lot
in my work elsewhere about the
importance of problem formulation
you've got to step back and spend a lot
of time really carefully
excavating right and explicating
your problem formulation if they turn if
you if you
if you get a sense that you're bashing
your head against the problem
that means stop trying to solve it
before
you do some heavy work at getting clear
about the problem formulation so that's
what we're going to do right now
amen and there and there are few uh more
difficult but more important things to
get our handle on
in the problem if we're dealing with
consciousness the language games are
you know just enormous exactly exactly
so the first argument
um i'm not i'm not going to be citing
descartes like word for word or verbatim
i'm trying to present the gist of the
argument um so the first argument
is is basically runs along these lines
and again i'm not going to worry about
getting this
um sort of technically logically
precisely valid
right we'll try to put our academic
training on the back end and just talk
like normal people
as much as possible right which is hard
for us people i
appreciate that yeah so
so the first argument goes like this
it's like
take a look at the properties of the
mind and we'll come back later to why
descartes zeroes in on these properties
take a look at the properties of the
mind the mind has
what's called intentionality okay what
does that mean that means
my mental states are about they're
directed at
they refer to things other than
themselves
um and material objects don't have that
this pencil is not about anything else
my thought about the pencil might be
but the pencil itself is not about
anything else doesn't refer to
it just is in itself it has causal
interactions with other things but it
has
nothing like intentionality and then
closely related to this
is mind mind is a place where there's
meaning
and and this is a this is the second of
the heart problem so i'm not going to
say too much about that
i'm just going to rely on your intuitive
sense that you for example
are getting the meaning of what i'm
saying right now
it's meaningful to you and you know and
many things your environment makes sense
to you it's meaningful to you
and so and but
material things obviously things don't
mean anything to this pencil
it doesn't make any sense to us in fact
if you had an experience where you
seriously thought
things were meaning being meaningful to
the pencil like you
like you'd you'd be questioning your
sanity you'd be checking me out in a
licensed sort of way
yes exactly well good okay and so
and then related to that is
your you you are oriented towards truth
and i say something
real fast about that because this is
important meaning
is in many ways automatic you see a red
cup and it
you intuit the affordances of this cup
it's just
the the machinery and we can talk i know
some more of that but highlight how
robust meaning comes to you simply
through your
perceptual awareness yeah we're going to
come back to this a lot
right one of one of my major proposals
is going to be
that a a deep way of trying to get at
this meaning that will connect it to
consciousness is through the idea of
relevance realization and that's what
greg is
alluding to right now uh and so we're
gonna come back to that
and so uh to continue uh my uh
i can evaluate uh my ideas or my
thoughts
in terms of whether they're true or
false again material things aren't true
or false
they just are and for think about how
strange this is how much does truth
weigh
what's its color how big is it i mean
these are all just absurd things to say
okay
so you can see that there are these deep
properties
of of mind and
matter seems to be completely lacking in
them
and then when we take a look at the
properties of matter
well you know it seems to have extension
it has resistance right it has
force physical force and of course
mental states don't have they're not
extended
right they don't have anything like
inertial resistance what would that mean
right they don't have energetic force
and you'll say but my ideas are forceful
to me
you're using a metaphor you're using a
metaphor and
we're going to come back to why do you
want to use those kinds of metaphors
right so what descartes noted was
he said well look mind seems to have
properties that are completely lacking
in matter
and matter seems to have properties that
are completely lacking in mind and
therefore
he drew this conclusion mind and matter
are two
separate independently existing
substances
this is known as cartesian dualism that
reality is made up of two
kinds of stuff
okay and so why is this first of all
important
many people carry around many people
have very confused ideas about
mind and body um and the relationship
between mind and brain and we'll come
back to that too
but many people do have and carry around
a kind of implicit dualism because
again this has become very prevalent in
our culture
and we'll see that descartes model got
integrated with a particular
interpretation of christianity
that also wove it into a lot of our
religious uh framework so it has
huge consequences so
what's the first thing to say about this
argument well let's go carefully with it
first of all the argument is not
technically a valid argument a valid
argument is one in which
the premises of the argument necessitate
the conclusion so if you accept the
premises
you must on pain of logical
inconsistency
a lot a deductive argument yes yes
so the pro why is it not technically
valid because in order for it to be
technically valid
the list of features has to be
exhaustive it has to be complete
so if descartes looks at three or four
properties what if the next 100
properties are shared by mind and matter
then adar's argument loses all of its
force right it loses all of its force
and you say well but maybe descartes got
them all he clearly did not
so now and this is going to be an
important move we have to set this
argument into its historical context
descartes for example was not aware of
unconscious cognition
most of us now understand that a crucial
feature of your cognition
is that most of it happens unconsciously
descartes did not have this
as a future of mine right he did not
have many of the features that we now
attribute to matter
he thought of matter almost as equal to
extension many of the properties
we now assign to matter like energy and
other baker did not
know that so his list is clearly clearly
not exhaustive or complete so right away
it's not technically valid
right and and let me just say uh you're
introducing two super important concepts
here
that are going to be crucial for us when
you get into the 20th century and then
ultimately 21st century for the right
language game
okay so the energy matter difference and
and relation
all right through uh james cork maxwell
and then ultimately
quantum mechanics and general relativity
that's unbelievably key
okay and the other thing is the
cognition versus consciousness
distinction yes
yes yes so those are both now diff we're
creating language systems that are
actually now
creating much more uh ticked rich
texture
in allowing us to narrate the landscape
excellent thank you great that's
excellent
so one way we could try and steal man
descartes right on his behalf is we
could say okay
but what descartes has found are the
essential properties
mind and matter so even if his list is
not exhaustive
at least he has the essential properties
and therefore we could restructure the
argument as
there's an essential difference between
mind and matter
and that at least makes it probable that
mind and matter might be
different substances okay that's fair
enough the problem is again
um claiming that we have the
the descartes of the essence of matter
is clearly false
um uh as as drake just said there's
there's lots more that
turned out to be essential so he does
not have the essence
he's claiming that we have the essence
of mind as greg is going to make really
clear uh
we can't agree on what
i mean a lot of breaks work in fact is
wrestling with the fact
that we can't agree on
like i mean academically culturally we
have no consensus
greg is laboring to try and bring about
this consensus
and he has to label in such a you know
heroic fashion precisely because there
is
so such a lack of consensus
about what the mental is it's a
fragmented pluralistic landscape
yes with with no grounding there's no
meta grounding
that allows a paradigmatic realization
so it's just it's just everybody has
different starting points different
emphases
uh it's very dramatic and and those
starting points have people get anchored
to
and uh so yeah that's why it's it's a
task
so many people um in fact that
this is this is a technical problem in
philosophy it's called the mark of the
mental
i'm trying to figure out even not even
the essence but even
a distinguishing mark of the mental that
will pick it out reliably
um so although we have intuitions uh
those intuitions don't reliably guide us
to an essence
and here's where you know here's where
again it intersects with science because
there's an argument by twine that says
largely one way of interpreting and i
think this is
a valuable thing to note about science
what science does is it finds those
categories that do have an essence
because when you find a category that
has an essence you can make broad
and deep generalizations inductive
generalizations
and that's what science is in the
business of doing and of course
well we might say that physics has made
a lot of progress towards that
uh it's very questionable that
psychology
has made a similar progress towards
producing
uh that kind of scientific success so
we we are not currently historically in
the place
where we could safely reconstruct
descartes argument as
here are the essential properties of
mind here are the essential properties
of matter
and therefore draw the conclusion okay
so what do we get so so well that was
easy
we just disposed of descartes right well
verveiki just disposed to descartes and
it's all solved and it's like that's
ridiculous
okay so the point we have the thing we
have to ask ourselves
if this is not a deductively valid
argument
why is it such a powerfully persuasive
argument and let's acknowledge the fact
that most of the good
arguments in science are not deductive
arguments in the first place okay
so here's the point i want to make i
wanna i
am proposing that what descartes does i
don't think descartes thought he was
doing this
i'm proposing a way to explain
why his arguments are so persuasive even
though they're not
deductively valid is that descartes
doing we can reconstruct his argument as
an inference to the best explanation
that descartes argument best explains
what's going on in the scientific
revolution
right he comes up with a way of
explaining the mind
that makes the best sense of the mind in
terms of the scientific revolution
and it's precisely because of that that
his view is so successful
so what i'm doing right from the
beginning is wedding the success
of his argument to the success of the
scientific revolution
what do you think about that i think
that's absolutely correct and
although maybe i i don't have quite the
appreciation for the connection between
descartes and say the catholic church
i certainly want to say that remember
modernist thinking is coming off of the
formal
uh scholastic academic tradition which
is dual world
okay so and if you have an embedded dual
world this mind body dualism is not
is part and parcel to your understanding
you die and your soul goes to heaven if
we think about it in concrete terms
you you fall asleep there's your body
your mind is wherever it is
you know and then you wake back up your
mind's back in action when you're you
know
so so we can empathize right away
with the intersection of christianity um
and dual world the idea that there's
some sort of enlighten you know
breath-giving soul that lights you up
uh that is separable from your body is
embedded in the grammar that comes
before in the western
european tradition here yes um and so
and then it's going to become this
psychological middle ground
even if descartes doesn't argue it in
terms of i talk a lot about how people
justify
you know so the idea that we can take
descartes and basically like okay we can
believe in this matter in motion stuff
but we still have a mind that's
separable for many people
that's going to create a psychological
uh maybe not
elegant philosophical solution but it
will create a psychological solution of
like oh okay we can believe in science
and still have our christian
version of reality i think that's
excellent um thank you
so i want to pick up so yeah i think
there's very much of two worlds
mythology
um that we've inherited uh from the
ancient world and through the medieval
world
that greg's right that's in there uh and
then
um part of the attraction of descartes
uh
yeah uh part of the attraction uh of
descartes argument is precisely how it
not only
is uh enmeshed with the scientific
revolution
it allows it we it
it re-languages christianity so that for
a while it has a safe space
within that emerging scientific
worldview so
perfect okay
so if how does let's just do a very
quick thing on infants to the best
explanation how does it work
uh and this is and the point about this
is descartes is playing fair i think
because
i would argue and uh many people there's
many people in philosophy of science
would argue that most of science works
in terms of
entrance to the best explanation so
let's i i believe that
so yeah so let's do it by an example
here's a very important scientific
theory uh
the darwin's theory of evolution so
what's the what's the issue well we have
some phenomena that
seems to demand from us explanation
creatures seem to be really well
designed in the sense of
their morphology and their behavior
seems to be really well fitted to the
environment that they're
in how did that happen right and
and we care about this because it has
implications for us
uh and so deep implications for us okay
so
you you can look around and now i'll be
paley who comes before darwin
well i can look around you know how does
how do some things get their shape
well you know sand dunes get their shape
by the wind blowing
oh well maybe the wind blows enough then
it will make a goat
that doesn't seem right okay i thought
that seems very very implausible
well you know maybe well sometimes
lightning strikes and it starts a fire
well maybe lightning strikes and it's
cites a particular kind of fire because
goats are warm
and that's how you get a goat and notice
how you're probably finding these
proposals ridiculous
and then you get well it's paley says
you know
think about this i come across a watch
and the watch is really complex
and compared to all these other
explanations here's a good explanation
for
how the watch came into existence
there's an intelligent designer that
made it and so compared to the other
explanations
we conclude because the explanation of
the intelligent designer
explains more and more precisely
than the other two and gives us you know
a
tighter fit between our explanations of
what we're trying to explain
we conclude that that's the case so
we put we have our we have our our
phenomena
we put a bunch of explanations into
competition and the one that does the
best job we conclude that the entities
that are proposed in it must therefore
exist
the intelligent designer for example now
darwin comes along and this shows you
something about inference to the best
explanation there are they are always
historically relative
because there's always more possible
explanations
always always darwin comes along
and he comes up with an alternative you
know
basically natural selection and the
thing about darwin is
his theory is a better explanation why
is it better
because he can explain not only really
good design but he can
explain really really crappy design like
you know why is our back have this weird
stupid s-curve in it
well because we have all done quadrupeds
right
um why do we have these wisdom teeth
that are you know
very not functional right well it's
because we have all right
and so he why does you know famously you
know google the panda's thumb why
doesn't the panda have a good thumb
why because right and so descartes
he can explain both good design and bad
design
and he can evoke entities that we can
observe
right he can we can observe competition
between animals
we can observe sexual reproduction or
just reproduction in general
so he has he
explains more phenomena in terms of
mechanisms for which we have more direct
evidence
so his proposal is the best
and that's why many people myself
included i know greg is too
think that this is the explanation of
how
you know organic creatures came to be
now notice
and this is actually happening right now
because people are now
and i mean within biology i don't mean
crackpots people within biology are
challenging darwin's account
and saying you know even the grand
synthesis
right has to be revised dennis walsh
a friend and colleague of mine is doing
fantastic work on this a bunch of other
people
because i've got ideas about that but
i'll spare you
so the point is when it
beats out the competition we conclude
that it's real
but we often we often forget that
inference to the best explanation is
historically relative
right if you before darwin if you didn't
believe
in intelligent design you were kind of
an idiot right
but after darwin it's really hard to
believe in intelligent design
and so that's where that's where we're
at okay so what i want to do
i'll make a quick plug here for
justification systems theory so
justification systems theory does
say that our ideas for what isn't ought
to be
exist in a socio-historical context and
justification is a key functional
dynamic so it just basically
if you have that frame you always are
then situating whatever justificatory
frame you have in its history yeah yeah
that's good
that's oh this is wonderful having you
here greg that's a great connection
and put those two together that's really
interesting so you what your
point greg is proposing make sure i
understand you greg he's proposing that
the epistemic strategy of inference to
the best explanation
is bound up with the social cultural
strategy
of justification which actually
constitutes
the cultural sphere did i understand you
correctly yeah and actually
when you get when you get used to the
language of justification it just
it permeates everything so it's like
well i'm justifying myself in a context
of justification and creates all these
weird
loops um but yeah that's exactly right
okay so what i want to do um is i want
to
do so i tried to convince you that
descartes argument
is an influence of the best explanation
and therefore
our approach to it has to be properly
historical and what that means is we
have to look at descartes time
at the competing explanations that were
on offer
and why did descartes model win out over
the competing explanations
and and let's remember that the arena
of the competition is the scientific
revolution
and as greg has reminded us it's also
the arena of the catholic church
in crisis because the protestant
reformation has occurred for example
yes of course okay
so what is on offer so first of all
what's on offer is the aristotelian
worldview
right so that's that's the that's the
official main competitor
right right so when you read sort of the
standard textbooks
uh the official main competitor is the
aristotelian
worldview and this was
uh undergoing uh something of a a very
powerful collapse
and this was not a trivial affair uh
because the aristotelian worldview had
been in
existence for had been dominant uh for
about
1800 years kind of thing
and so that's a long time and it had
deeply
inseminated uh catholic theology like
thomas aquinas
had deeply stitched uh christianity and
the aristotelian worldview
uh together and the educational system
the scholastic tradition that greg
alluded to
was deeply woven with aristotelian ideas
about
learning and the cultivation of virtue
so right this was this was the
so a good thing to ask is what was the
scientific revolution revolting against
it was revolting against the
aristotelian worldview
right and the uh again if you for to
get a more complex view of that i refer
people to some of the episodes from
awakening for the meeting crisis
go ahead greg i'll i'll make a quick
comment here because actually
what i'm really interested in is just in
this it gets back to some of my stuff so
i won't go
onto but actually there's an explosion
of um
what i would call pure lame metaphysics
okay around the 15th century all right
16th century
if you do purely metaphysics everything
is tautological
okay uh so it's so you get aristotle's
metaphysics
combined with the catholic church and
then on steroids
where that where you can't and then
galileo hates that
so galileo's empiricism isn't defined
against
metaphysics gone wild we should do a
video on that
metaphysics gone wild no so anyway
so that's in that tradition so that
tradition is collapsing
and that's actually going to come back
because i actually think that we do a
disservice to metaphysics
at least the natural modern empirical
science doesn't realize that you need a
descriptive metaphysics for your
empiricism
so anyway that's uh and i i i've got to
argue there's aspects of
aristotle or that come back oh
absolutely
especially at the issues of life mind
and culture when we get into final and
uh uh formal causation i don't know if
you want to get into that but that's a
whole another excitement
well we will so so
i'm gonna like i said let's talk about
what was lost
uh what was being lost in the scientific
revolution what was being
uh dispensed with in from the aristotel
world view
uh so uh
a useful way to look at how people are
living their metaphysics is in terms of
their worldview
and a worldview some of you recognize
this argument from elsewhere it's made
up of two components
a model of the world and a model of your
viewing your knowing
of the world knowing broadly construed
and they have to mutually support each
other in a very
very powerful fashion and like craig uh
just said
that can that can degenerate into a kind
of empty tautology
kind of thing greg wasn't saying that
the
worldview was itself a tautology no no
but that attunement can be
misappropriated as a empty kind of
tautology
so um what's the theory of viewing the
theory of viewing is the conformity
theory
again i'm not going to go into this
detail you can take a look at some of
the videos from
i'll put links in the notes we can go to
specific extended arguments about this
from awakening for the meeting crisis
but the basic idea
is that what makes something
intelligible
is its structural functional
organization
and that what i do when i know something
is
my mind actually takes on the same
structural functional organization
as the thing so
shape is only a metaphor for structural
functional organization if you sort of
integrate
uh our ideas of shape with the idea of
like
a chemical structure or a biological
structure you're getting closer to what
i'm talking about when i'm talking about
structural functional organization but
i'll use shape
as a metaphor for structural functional
organization
and so my in my hand my mind is
my hand and we use the word grasp for
knowing i grasp something or i
comprehend it my hand literally takes on
the
shape it takes on the same structural
functional organization
as the thing it possesses so there is a
deep identity between my mind
and the thing that is known this is what
is called the conformity theory
so i want you to notice the deep
connectedness the intimacy even
the identification between the mind and
what is known yep okay
so that is actually being destroyed
and so most of us don't think of that
today
what did the science what was the
scientific revolution doing well
the the scientific revolution was
challenging the idea
that our mind had this intimate even uh
identification with intimate connection
and into
identification with why because
aristotle had said this is how you can
tell
if your mind is in conformity you do you
do a bunch of checks you make sure the
relevant organ is functioning
you make sure the medium that's
operating in is not distorting and you
make sure you have interpersonal
agreement
and this is what we do in our day-to-day
lives but we want to know if something's
real
i want to make sure are my glasses clean
right
right is is it foggy or
or did you see that too bob and susan oh
absolutely
all right that's gonna get that
correspondence going
yeah exactly and so and now aristotle
said now
he didn't mean just sort of like uh uh
you know whimsical or everyday sense he
said
you do it you know really you you do it
very philosophically you do a lot of
rational reflection in the discussion
and you do all this very careful work
and then after you pass those three
tests
then you know that the form in your mind
and the form in the world are conformed
together
and then copernicus copernicus comes
along
and we'll come back to copernicus later
but what's he what's he doing he's
saying
you know what we can all get up
we're stone cold sober our eyes are all
20 20 vision
it's a clear day there's a bunch of us
around
and we're talking and we're making sure
we're checking with each other and we
all
see the sun rise in the east pass
overhead and set in the west and we are
all wrong right we're all wrong
in fact and why did he say that so
remember this
he said that because as he said it
because putting the sun at the center
and having the earth go around it and
turn on its axis
made the math work better we're going to
come back to that
so what's what happens is
copernicus and then galileo say rather
than experience
being the moment of conformity
experience is
actually something that fails us from
the world
it blinds us to the world we need the
math to get through the veil
to get to the thing and so what is born
is the idea that knowing happens through
representation i have to have something
that because the thing
is not present to my mind in conformity
i have to have
some other thing that represents it
the world to my mind exactly so yeah
we get this idea that the mind is
inherently representational and it is
cut off from the world and that
most of experience is therefore
illusory in some important fashion
so i'll stop there for a second give
greg a chance to uh interject and
respond
yes i mean i i will certainly we can
suggest that this idea
is present certainly in the greeks if we
go to plato and think about the allegory
of the cave there's allusion to this
notion that we are suggesting about the
mind representation
but the break with what um
you know the copernican world view uh is
really
you know people just hadn't thought
about it you know it's really kind of
remarkable not to say
but really the idea was that the heavens
had to conform
to perfect circles of our earth and you
know of our mind
um so the earth shattering nature of of
this
uh heliocentric transition is really
remarkable and it does set the stage
for an enormous profound justification
dilemma of like well what is the ground
upon which we are
uh legitimizing uh because and so
your story about this narrative i just
want people to realize how
world view foundational shaking it is
um when when that conformity thing slips
away
and people now are like well wait a
minute maybe we're all bs you know this
would come back to
uh renee descartes evil demon you know
in relationship to what
the possibility of that
well said so notice what's happening
here the on one the mind is withdrawing
into itself from the world
what's happening on the other side what
was the model of the world and greg
already pointed to it
under aristotle it's a geocentric world
view because what is the structure of my
experience
the structure of my experiences i'm at
the center and things are moving around
me and they seem to be moving in perfect
circles
right and all of that falls apart
and it falls apart because what we're
getting much better measurements
much better and we're getting much
better math and algebra is coming in
uh from the arab world and so we're
getting
right and we're seeing that the heavens
mars is doing this weird retrograde and
things are just behaving strangely
and as i mentioned copernicus said well
if we put the sun at the center the math
works better
and so mathematical representations
are now going to be much more
trustworthy than all of this
right stop and pause because think about
what that means for consciousness
already you go from thinking of
consciousness as something
that is putting you in contact with
reality
to being something that's somehow in the
mind
because all of this of which unconscious
all of this qualitative
structured meaningful experience it's
not out there
because it's not mathematically
measurable
it's not there it's not there all so
for example in aristotle's worldview
things are moving on purpose
everything is moving on purpose because
everything every element is trying to
get
to where it belongs everything is moving
on purpose
but galileo discovers immersion inertial
motion
things aren't moving on purpose they're
not
think about what's at the heart of the
word inertia inert
lifeless purposeless dead right
so everything is moving not on purpose
and now the fact that we move on purpose
is again
well we're it's not like we're doing
what everything else is doing
we're now doing something really weird
and unique
that seems to be and what's happening
you see i keep doing it with my hands
we go from the mind and you know
consciousness being a way in which we
are
affined and identified to the world to
be
no no all of these properties are
actually withdrawing and they're
completely
in the subject they're exactly
subjective
right here right and all that's out
there is what the math
represents to me the mathematical
properties are the real are the
properties in the object
so so this is unbelievably crucial to
understand the dilemma that we're in i
often refer to
as the modernist empirical and we can
get into this word empiricals a very
interesting word because it used to mean
basically first person experience and
then it means
exterior third-person measurement and
observation in the science switch so
there's a switch
and what the science then stops doing
is it it it becomes unbelievably suspect
of the subject
okay i often call it the anti-knower and
what i mean by this the anti-subjective
bias knower that tries to get to
objectivity so it's trying to
cross out that subjective perspective
and give rise to a general observer
third person view
how do you do that through mathematical
logic measurement
and a gen some sort of generic observer
that interprets that measurement so we
are so we're really transforming
um our epistemology here very very
profoundly excellent
so let's pick up on that so notice
what's happening here
copernicus isn't trying to do anything
about the mind
he's trying to solve a problem of making
sense
of the new sciences understanding
emerging new sciences understanding of
the heavens
and yet that immediately ramifies into
this
grammar that galileo is going to develop
that craig just talked about
of the subjective and objective and all
of these properties that were
previously in the world are now
withdrawing into the mind and are being
regarded as illusory
and only subjective in existence you see
the very project of like the scientific
revolution is
driving us into a way
of thinking about the world and the mind
that is pulling them apart and setting
them against each other
which is very opposite to the
aristotelian view
that had them deeply conforming and
mutually
defining of each other so
can we let's just for the if we're
thinking to connect this back to the
meaning crisis
you know our i mean obviously there's
other philosophy going on here but our
foundational epistemological oh this is
what truth
is okay it's now cutting out the
subjective knower
and the meaning that it represents about
the world
okay so this is a very very profound
element of what the modernist
mentality is going to mean downstream
here
in terms of what we're going to be
dealing with so i just let the viewer
think about the implications of that
i want to i want to riff on that a sec
it's also desiccating the world
yeah well oh yeah it leaves the world
desiccated also
um and so we are cut out from
the scientific world view that's
sort of this direction that greg pointed
to and i'm also pointing out
we can't we can't find ourselves at home
in that world
because it doesn't have any of the
properties that make our experiencing
make our experience meaningful to us in
any deep fashion
amen but and this is actually going back
to galileo
and what he takes from aristotle's
metaphysics in terms of
empirical uh substance and efficient or
really kinetic cause
okay and he's going to kill formal and
final causation that's exactly what i
was going to move into next
so maybe so what is also happening as
like just said
is like the kind uh so
galileo basically we we
we think of this as so natural that
you do science by doing math think about
you like
and we graph and we do there is no math
in aristotelian science
there's no math they had math the greeks
invented mathematics it's not like they
didn't they invented formal mathematics
they had it they had formal logic
aristotle invents it so they had it
but the idea that you do science by
applying math
that's not in the aristotelian world
view but galileo
does this and then he proposes that that
because of what copernicus says is i can
use the math
in order to overcome the way in which my
experience is so deceptive
right i can use the map and what i have
to do is i have to set up the world
so i can mathematically measure and
manipulate it
because that's the way in which i will
be able to
overcome the self-deception and that's
where you start to get the experimental
method
you start to get the experimental method
development and what happens
as greg said when you do this is
that as the conform as the
gap is opening up and as the
representation
that what is our primary connection to
the world
all of these properties notice what
we've talked about all of these
properties of purpose
are being removed purpose and meaning
and so and galileo is discovering
inertial motion
and so he thinks that the only way
things happen is through contact
efficient causation
things this is the billiard ball model
they have to bang
things have to con so notice what what's
happening here
right is that the that the only
way in which they can understand
causation is through things because the
things are
because things are inert there's no
dynamic to them because all purpose and
meaning has been removed to them
the only way they can interact is by
inertially
smashing into each other right matter in
motion yeah so we get
the essence of this matter in motion
where we can independently observe with
mathematics
entities and their change and now and
now that says now this becomes the
conceptual grammar the lens through
which
we will make sense of the material world
and then the question is well where
is that everything right and now we're
going to get into this well
but there's this other stuff
so let's try and gather together
what we've got is we've lost the
conformity theory
and the geocentric worldview and that's
made so many of the properties
of the world actually estranged from the
world
and then we have to house them into this
new conception of the mind
as this self-enclosed separate substance
that is actually cut off from reality
and that can only get you through
reality uh through
math and through mathematical
representation
and that the only thing therefore it can
pick up on
in the world the only real relations
that things have to each other the only
only real causal uh relation that exists
are things physically coming into
contact with each other
banging into each other
okay what else happens there
well this was a i i was i was fortunate
as an undergraduate to study with albert
shalom and he made this argument
about the loss of the aristotelian
worldview a further consequence of it
which is the function of the mind um
the mind used to this is going to this
is going to be the hardest part
um what used to be called the mind it
wasn't really the mind
but in aristotle you know
the mind was basically the dynamic
development of the structural functional
organization
so mine's job was to
actualize the potential of matter so
aristotle had a notion of matter but
it's very different from odds
so for aristotle it's helpful to use the
greek word for matter hulei
which originally meant wood right so
aristotle said well
from the same block of wood i could make
a chair or a table
or i might make a small ship right
and so the wood is potentially a chair
or a table what makes it actually a
table
or a chair is how it's structurally
functionally organized
it has been informed a particular form
structural functional organization
has been put into it so that it acts in
a certain way
so matter is potential that is
actualized by structural functional
organization
and then living creatures and especially
mental creatures have a dynamic
capacity for actualization and so the
mind for
aristotle is that about us which at many
level is
actualizing the potential of our body
and our interaction
so the mind is actually a developmental
actualizer of all of the potentiality
that is given to you
yep so and and so we can say actually so
you know in his word is psyche by the
way okay that really is
soul but it's the functional form of the
entities
all right and then i get all excited
because he's going to put this on a
scale of natura
right and then he's going to say there's
inanimate functional forms and then
there's
vegetative functional forms and then
there's animal functional forms
and then they're rational personal
functional forms if you know tree of
knowledge matter life mind and culture
there's going to be a lot of overlap in
relationship to there but
so he is thinking about functional form
uh at these different
levels of nature and that really
mine he don't really have the equivalent
of the term mind he has this functional
form
that jumps off of the material plane and
gets into the vegetative
animal and rational planes right
excellent
and as you're going up the scale of
actualization you're coming into
entities that are more and more capable
yes of actualizing them right have more
complicated
you know functional structural forms and
doing
you know uh more and more sophisticated
things
so you have this whole model of the mind
as
an engine of dynamical development and
emergence
right which actually isn't a bad model
and here's the thing we lose that this
is shalom's point
we lose that when the aristotelian view
is lost and so we lose
the job of mind being inherently
connected to development
and emergence we lose the function of
mind as being inherently connected
to development and emergence so now the
mind is
not only isolated it doesn't really have
any important relationship to the body
it's not actualizing the body
and it is not inherently in development
it is just
an epistemic engine its only job is to
represent the world as mathematically
accurately as possible
brilliant brilliant i'll make a quick
point here
i i've detailed in depth uh
john watson you know a famous
behaviorist
and he has a footnote he basically says
to the extent there's any problem of
consciousness
it's a philosophical problem to
legitimize epistemology
okay that's what he says he's like you
know because he has this neural network
reflex model that reduces to all this
mechanical stuff so he's like to the
extent
it's a problem of just philosophers and
epistemology about what an observation
is
and how do you legitimize it so so it's
really cool about how much he's
internalized that as a behavior you know
the raw behaviorism right internalizes
this and then
he still has to see somehow cautious
plays a role well he skirted it all the
way up
to the problem of epistemology and the
profession of philosophy
it's really interesting that's pretty
cool i didn't know that
yeah thank you greg that's very good
so notice what we now have we have the
aristotelian
view is collapsing why is the
aristotelian view collapsing
because it doesn't do well with the
science at all it doesn't do well with
the emerging science
at all instead the science
is driving and this is not to say that
science is evil that is not what we're
saying
i'm not saying that yeah i don't think
john and i are going to be in that camp
so but what the what the scientific
revolution is doing it's revolting
against the erythrian worldview
and we're losing right we're losing
purpose and final causation
we're losing a picture of the mind as
functioning in development and in
emergence we're losing the idea of the
mind
being intimately connected to the world
and that meaning
is uh something that all the things that
we find meaningful are disclosing uh
aspects of the world
instead the mind is now a place where
all of the properties that can no longer
exist
in matter have to be found so the beauty
of the rose
isn't anything out there because it's
not a mathematical property it's just in
here
the sweetness of the honey the sunrise
and sunset are not there
they're just subjective they're just
illusions
right all of it is an illusion
and so you get this self-enclosed
mind that has a single
basic function all it's doing
is trying to create mathematically
accurate representations of the world
and so the mind is basically
struggling against the fact that it is
filled with
all of these properties that don't
belong in the world
and it's trying to use mathematical
representation
because that's the only way in which the
world can be present to it
again right that's what a scientific
mind is trying to do
exactly exactly okay so notice
notice what what we're getting here so
this will allow us to introduce one
technical term we will try to keep these
to a minimum
so philosophers so galileo
proposes a distinction between sort of
primary and secondary qualities that
descartes takes up
and then lock takes up etc to get just
taken it
so the primary qualities are the
properties of things the qualities of
things
that are mathematically measurable and
therefore
they are objective they are in the
object
all the properties that are not
mathematically measurable are secondary
qualities and they only subjectively
exist they only exist in the mind
and now you have a place for all these
secondary
qualities so philosophers have a name
for these secondary qualities we call
them qualia
the qualia they're they're all of the
the
the the the felt meaningful aspects of
our experience
that we don't think are actually in the
world so we have the qualia
and then of course we have a place for
the qualia and that place
we start to call consciousness
consciousness is the self-enclosed
place where the qualia are found and
where
purpose and development and
self-actualization or whatever
everything retreats there and and so
what you have is this notion
so let's i'm going to come back to this
in descartes second argument but here's
the the notion
the mind was once in conformity to the
world and
charles taylor calls this a contact
epistemology or so i keep using contact
what happens is the only thing that the
mind is now
in contact with is itself
and that contact with itself are the
qualia
when the mind is touching itself those
are the purely subjective
qualia that's consciousness
consciousness is the mind touching
itself in acts of qualia
and that's how we started and notice how
this is
completely subjective as opposed to
objective
and notice that it is something that is
by definition
not mathematically measurable and
therefore
completely other than the external world
so descartes argument comes along and he
looks at this and he says
you know why that's the case people
didn't think this was the case a hundred
years before descartes
but everybody's confronting these ideas
now descartes says you know why that's
the case
because mind and matter are actually two
fundamentally different kinds of
substance
they share no properties they're unique
and distinct from each other
and in comparison to the aristotelian
worldview they can't explain
all of this what's going on in the
scientific revolution descartes argument
makes
perfect sense it explains why we are
coming to all of these conclusions about
qualities
and properties and how the earth is
actually going around the sun
and that we there is no purpose out
there and the only thing the mind does
is know the world
it explains all of this perfectly in a
way in which
the aristotelian framework does not
and so that's one way in which his
argument
is beating out the aristotelian
worldview
i want to put out one other there's one
other contender
that is not normally talked about in the
official textbook okay
and this is part of the history and we
need to mention this because
there's a sense in which greg and i want
to bring back at least
aspects of this contender into uh what
we want to talk about
so uh cedar talks about this and a
couple other people
mark taylor talks a lot about this in
his book i believe after god
talks about that there was actually a
third contender uh that was actually
very prevalent
and this was the neoplatonic magical
tradition
uh that was coming out in the late
renaissance
the fact that we even call it magic
means we've already got this whole
way in which we marginalized it and
excluded it
uh and you know and so and
rightly so like even when i when i utter
that word i sort of there's part of me
that goes
right but let's let's try and situate it
historically
what were the neoplatonic uh
philosophers
magicians pointing to well they were
pointing to
things that didn't fit into either the
aristotelian worldview or the new
cartesian worldview
they were saying but wait there seems to
be action at a distance
there seems to be magnetism and
why are things falling if they're not
moving on purpose like aristotle said
descartes
why when i like how does the earth
the earth is it touching the pen and yet
it's drawn like what's going on
there's action out of the distance and
they're looking at living things and
they're saying
but living things are self-organizing
right they're self-they don't use that
term but that's right right
using terms that's exactly what they're
pointing to they're dynamic
they're self-organizing they're
inherently developmental using more
modern language they seem to have
emergent properties
and so action at a distance and
emergence and self-organizing
and they're trying to say we need to
make these the centerpiece
if they had won biology would have been
the first primary
science other than physics right
and it's only now that biology is coming
into its core
if you compare the sort of theoretical
advance
in the two sciences biology is showing
way more theoretical advance right now
than physics is
and that isn't uh a coincidence by the
way
i'm not saying that physics is bad or
they're not generating all kinds of data
i'm talking about a very specific point
about theoretical advance
okay so let's go back to the neoplatonus
they're saying all this
and the catholic church is looking at
all this and it's like oh my gosh
the aristotelian world war is collapsing
but we're thomas and we don't want to
lose that
and initially descartes descartes is bad
this is not good
galileo's bad galileo is almost like
always
rest right but while as descartes is put
on house duress
bruno is actually burnt at the stake and
he's one of those neoplatons
now why why does the church regard
fitness is even more dangerous well
because
if if if it's natural
for there to be action at a distance
then
miracles aren't all that strange
everything has the potent and this is
why they're thought of as being magical
everybody could potentially bring about
action at a distance
lifeless magnets bring about action and
distance surely human beings could
develop a kind of
magnetism as we're much later right
and also they're miraculous and if
things are self-organizing and emergent
well you don't need a creator so you
don't need god the father
and you don't need jesus in his miracles
and
oh no whoa right
that's really dangerous that's like
witch's stuff
so it's like you know what
let's actually embrace the cartesian
world of view
with inertial motion and only efficient
causation
because it will it strangles out and
prevents
that
no that's a i was talking about the
psychological utility of
of the cartesian view you just added a
whole another dimension of justification
that i wasn't aware of in relationship
to the pressures that would give rise to
that fusion so now
not only is it a psychological middle
ground of science in
the old but it's actually now also a
defense against a potential in
incursion right excellent and so what
gets pushed to a side
are organic dynamic emergent
right embodied embedded approaches to
cognition
that are only now very much later
resurfacing in what's called 4e
cognitive science it's taken that long
and right to to to get back to where
we can now talk about the kinds of
things that the neoplatonists
wanted to talk about and so what happens
is
a large part of the catholic church
aligns and this is what
what i i was trying what greg was
alluding to about
why the catholic church aligns
with descartes because by aligning with
the cartesian
framework it can actually especially one
that's getting
all of the uh the uh approval of the
emerging scientific revolution
then it can have a ball work against
this other view
that is much more dangerous uh to
the the catholic worldview the christian
worldview
and descartes dualism as greg rightly
alluded
gives you a way of re-conceptualizing
and now we
we take it for granted but
reconceptualizing the soul
and what descartes does is he says well
you know this this completely
self-enclosed
mental stuff that is completely not
material
that's what a soul is a soul is
completely self-enclosed
mental stuff aristotle would have said
what are you talking about that makes no
sense to me
right you know and so what happens is
you get something that we all now take
for granted
you get the equation of soul
with the conscious mind
that that's what the soul is and that
and then the conscious mind
is equated with a self-enclosed
separable immaterial substance and then
the catholic church has a new way of
thinking about soul
that gives keeps it independent from
independent from being crushed away by
the scientific worldview
now i want to be clear i am not accusing
descartes of
engaging in propaganda because he's
trying to save the catholic church
descartes is a catholic but his
arguments
are they have to be taken on their own
merits because they were taken on their
own marriage
but what i am saying is the reverse is
the case there's a huge branch of the
catholic church
that actually gets attracted to
descartes ideas because it squeezes out
the neoclateness with scientific
legitimacy
and it gives a reconceptualization of
the soul
that will preserve it from the emerging
from the emerging collapse
of the aristotelian worldview
yes
in a way that is almost
imperceptibly complex this
idea of consciousness
is bound up via these right via this
competition this influences them
descartes wins because his argument
functions best
to get rid of the aristotelian right
out the neil plaitness and rehome the
soul
right so it's just insinuated
throughout it's woven through the
scientific world view
and the now emerging christian worldview
the new the the post descartes
christian world view and so what we're
seeing here is the intersection between
these large-scale systems of
justification
that are institutionalized and narrating
their structures right at the
sociocultural level
as we try to narrate what is going on at
this human psychological level
you know at the subjective the interface
between all of this
is why we got a world knot of
consciousness you know
so i i think we're getting to a place
maybe where we can start to wrap up
uh this uh portion of the conversation
yeah so i think that's what we should do
but uh so you know
we we've taken the title of this from
schopenhauer's quote that you know the
mind body problem is the world not
and we chose the world not precisely
because we
and this is what this argument is trying
to show this isn't a problem
about sort of you know here's some
features of consciousness and here's
some features of the
the natural world right uh it's it's it
is a world not
you know our our our our our scientific
world view
and the and our religious heritage
whether or not we're christians
doesn't matter that has has been sewn
into our cultural cognitive grammar in a
deeper way
what i'm trying to show you is the
cartesian model
of consciousness is born up with those
in an inseparable fashion
one up with that whole heritage in an
inseparable fashion and then you say
well that's great
i like the dualism no well i'm gonna
leave you with why it's problematic and
then next time greg and i will come back
and look at david's second argument
we're gonna keep doing this here's why
it's problematic and descartes knew this
and everybody immediately said staycard
knew it and they they saw it as the deep
the deepest problem
so everybody says yes descartes must be
right for all the reasons we've given
but how is it possible that
mind or consciousness and matter
interact because the whole point of this
is dualism
the whole point is they share no
properties whatsoever
how could the truth of my idea
in any way affect the
matter of my body my bad my body has to
be moved by some other
matter that has physical energy it has
inertial properties
that has electromagnetic radiation my
ideas and the truth of my idea
of none of those properties but yet i'm
going to do it i want to move my finger
hey there you go
it moved how did mine move matter or the
opposite
so i had my hand on the table at the
completely material contact
galileo's right things smashing into
each other but it results in
pain which is a
completely subjective
qualia how did something
physical caught an objective
and energetic cause pain
which is subjective and not
and so this is this is what's known as
the mind-body problem we can even call
it the consciousness
world problem or the consciousness
matter problem
right that's to me yep and and do you
remember the
duchess or lady because over descartes
overlooks this in his first
round of this and he gets it pointed out
to him and i'm blanking on her name i
think it's elizabeth from sweden who
doesn't know
okay anyway so she asked them this very
question of course and this gets to the
pineal gland answer which is not
adequate back to this
right so and everybody takes it up
spinoza takes it up and lives and it
takes
leibnitz takes it up and mall branch
everybody
and and you can there's a sense in which
this is the problem
that everybody we can't ignore this
question
because the solution that descartes
proposed
while elegant in its ability to deal
with the scientific world view
and the christian worldview and hold
them together
and give people an existential response
to all of the trauma that's happening
well it's elegant in all of those ways
gives us this
like what seems like an insolvable
problem
there seems to be no possible way in
which mind
and matter can interact and yet
everything about us
tells us everything we're doing every
moment of our experience
every knowledge claim we make everything
what i claim to know greg's
knowledge i came to know greg's mind
i just claim to have knowledge of it but
all i see is his material body
how could i possibly go from his
material body to his mind
it can't causally interact so we're
going to come back to this in the way in
which
the mind-body problem is also a problem
of other minds
no reason for attributing mind to
anybody else
because the only way mind can be known
is consciousness of itself
and for all my affection for greg i do
not
know his mind that way that's right
yep right and so so here we have the
knot
the knot has been tied uh but we can
leave little clues here if we go back
and we say okay
if you remember our first thing we i put
up that sort of okay we're going to work
through this mind right mind123
we have we can identify with aristotle
and the functional conformity we can see
a functional
active mind kind of notion you know it
starts with plants and then
dogs do it and then people do it okay
and that's going to be actually going to
connect to our mind one
version of reality and then we have also
connected this notion about this
narrative and institutional
justification
and argument okay which is going to be
mind three
and now we're really honing in on what
what we're meaning in our western
tradition
this contained subjective
representational phenomenological
portion
of mind uh and then that becomes
consciousness and then how does that
connect
uh is you know where you know these are
two domains we're gonna give a
vocabulary to them but we're going to be
left
with this problem so but we're going to
try and shrink it as much as we can
we're going to shrink that thing and
we're going to box it in and we're going
to show
that with additional language categories
and
an upgraded version of uh scientific
ontology and epistemology
this thing can be much more effectively
addressed yes and that again will ramify
back
in terms of the existential and
spiritual consequences
it will actually feed back in important
ways to addressing the media crisis
absolutely okay so uh we're going to
meet again
um and greg and i are we've both
committed to this long term
because we both think the journey has
been engaged
yeah and so next time what i want to do
is
uh present uh the sec we're going to
take a look at danger's three arguments
because the three arguments are
important
um and we'll go through that and then
we'll set up the history
and then i'm going to turn it over to
greg for a while and
he'll he's going to talk about how this
ramifies
into the scientific project of
psychology
and then we're going to gather it up
together into what are the current
cognitive scientific theories of
consciousness the people the attempts
people are making
to give a scientific explanation of
consciousness
that addresses all of descartes
arguments
but doesn't leave us with descartes
problems
okay everyone amen uh next time
take good care everyone thanks so much
my good friend thank you thank you it's
brilliant yep
no thank you